Finding Aid for the Charles Faulkner Bryan Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
The Charles Faulkner Bryan Collection
2007
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0058
.42 linear feet
Biographical Note
Charles Faulkner Bryan was born in McMinnville, Tennessee on July 26, 1911.
He became one of Tennessee’s most important musicians, composers, and collectors of folk music, and he had a career as a music educator most notably at Tennessee Polytechnic Institute and at George Peabody College for Teachers. While at Peabody he and George Pullen Jackson co-authored a textbook for the teaching of music in the schools. In 1946 Bryan studied with Paul Hindemith at Yale on a Guggenheim Fellowship. There he began and completed his famous work The Bell Witch Cantata which had its premier at Carnegie Hall in 1947 under the direction of Robert Shaw. Bryan incorporated black spirituals, white spirtuals, and Appalachian folk tunes masterfully in his work, and he is known especially for The White Spiritual Symphony ( 1942) and the folk opera Singin’ Billy (1952) On this he worked with Fugitive poet and Agrarian and Vanderbilt professor Donald Davidson, and much of the correspondence in this collection relates to this cooperative venture between Bryan and Davidson.
In the last years of his life he was Master of Music at Indian Springs School in Alabama. He died suddenly on July 7, 1955 at the age of 43 leaving an important legacy of understanding of American folk lore and culture through his work as a musician and teacher. He was married to Edith Hillis in 1935, and they had two children, Betty Lynn and Charles, Jr. In Warren County Tennessee in the park in front of the courthouse there is an historical marker which honors Bryan’s achievements and reads:
“A native of Warren County, Bryan was a pioneer in the study of American folk music. Through his talented efforts this distinctively American form of musical expression gained worldwide fame and appreciation. He worked closely with the people of the Southern mountains and coves in the study of this music, but his work earned a permanent place of honor and distinction in the highest ranks of academic and scholarly achievement. Presented in his memory by a grateful community.”
Scope and Content Note
This collection is .42 linear feet, one Hollinger box, of materials relating to Charles Faulkner Bryan and it includes photocopies of correspondence between Bryan and Donald Davidson, with whom he collaborated on the musical Singin’ Billy.
Also in this collection is sheet music of pieces by Bryan and includes the Songs for Children Series, the Bell Witch Secular Folk Cantata, Tennessee Folk Songs and other music by Bryan. There are two 8 x 10 photographs of Bryan in this small collection.
- File Listing
  - Photocopies of Correspondence
    - Outgoing, September 28, 1948 - September 5, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Outgoing, September 21, 1953 - December 7, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Outgoing, January 9, 1954 - June 14, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photocopies of Correspondence with Donald Davidson
    - Incoming, October 14, 1950 - November 8, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Incoming, June 4, 1952 - July 13, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Incoming, August 15, 1952 - December 14, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Incoming, January 4, 1953 - March 29, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Incoming, April 2, 1953 - May 27, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Incoming, June 2, 1953 - August 25, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Incoming, September 4, 1953 - December 13, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Incoming, January 8, 1954 - August 30, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Incoming, September 13, 1954 - December 20, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Incoming, December 27, 1954 - December 8, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sheet Music
    - “The Area of a Regular Polygon” (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - “Arma Virumque Cano” words from Vergil’s Aeneid (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The Bell Witch – Secular Folk Cantata (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sheet Music
    - “Down the Road”; “I Heard the Bells on Christmas Day”; “Longing”; “To a Hall” (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - “Flower in the Crannied Wall” words by Alfred, Lord Tennyson (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - “The Hawthorn Tree” (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - “The Low Country” from Singin’ Billy (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Songs for Children, “About Buttons” “The Circus Parade” “The Doctor” (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Songs for Children, d. “Fireflies” e. “Gas Station Man” f. “Go to Sleep” (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Songs for Children, g. “Hippity Hop” h. “If a Pig Wore a Wig” i. “Mary Middling” j. “Mary Middling #2” (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Songs for Children, k. “The Postman” l. “Rain” m “Snow” n. “The Tractor” (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - “East Gospel” and “Peace in the Valley” from Strangers in this World words by Brainard Cheney and music by C.F. Bryan (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Tennessee Folk Songs collected by George Boswell; arranged by Charles F. Bryan for use in the Tennessee public schools, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - “Then” by William Stafford and C.F. Bryan (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - “These are the Times” by Thomas Paine and C.F. Bryan (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - “These are the Times” by Thomas Paine and C.F. Bryan (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Other
    - Libretto for Singin’ Billy: An Opera in Two Acts by Charles F. Bryan and Donald Davidson for a performance at George Peabody College, August 9, 10, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Program - Dedication Ceremony - Bryan Fine Arts Building, Nov. 14, 1981, Tennessee Technological University, Cookeville, Tennessee (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Article - “Falconhurst: A Legend of Place and People” in Tennessee Magazine, September 1983 with an accompanying letter from Mrs. Bryan, September 15, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Photograph - Charles Faulkner Bryan (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Photograph - Robert Shaw congratulating Charles F. Bryan at rehearsal of the Bell Witch Cantata in Carnegie Hall, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 34)